Register of the Alexis Borisovich Tatistcheff Papers, 1766-1977
Hoover Institution Archives
Alexis Borisovich Tatistcheff Papers,
1768-1977
Bulk, 1870-1977
77014
Hoover Institution Archives
7 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes, 1 card box, 1 scrapbook (6.7 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, writings, printed matter, and photographs, relating to the Russian nobility, the Romanov dynasty, the Russian Revolution and Civil War, and Soviet-American relations during the 1960s and 1970s.
Tatistcheff, Alexis Borisovich,
Access
Collection open for research.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1977.
Separated Materials
The Printed matter series has been separated from the collection to the Hoover Institution Library.
Biographical/Historical note
Alexis Borisovich Tatistcheff, an economist and language expert, served as an interpreter for the State Department. Mr. Tatistcheff, who was born in Berlin, where his father served in the Russian Embassy, was educated at the Ecole des Travaux Publiques in Paris and came to the United States in 1926. Mr. Tatistcheff was chief statistician at the Commodity Exchange and in 1941 was named principal economist in the Federal Bureau of Research and Statistics in the Office of Production Management, later known as the War Production Board. His linguistic abilities - he was fluent in French, Russian and English - came to the attention of the State Department, and in 1945 he served as an interpreter at the United Nations Conference in San Francisco. Helped Marshall in London. Mr. Tatistcheff was named assistant chief of the division of language service for the State Department and was an interpreter with Secretary of State George C. Marshall at the London Conferences in 1947. Then he joined the Merrill Lynch investment concern as manager of its hide and rubber department, but after a year he left to become a consultant to the State Department. In 1975 Mr. Tatistcheff was chief interpreter and adviser to the National Aeronautics and Space Administration in negotiations for a joint Soviet-United States space flight. For his work with NASA, he received the Government's Public Service Award. From 1976 to 1979, he was an interpreter for the United States delegations at the Strategic Arms Limitation Treaty talks in Helsinki and Geneva. Died in 1990.
Scope and Contents note
Collection consist primarily of materials collected by Alexis Borisovich Tatistcheff and includes memoirs, original documents, photographs, correspondence, clippings, and print materials, providing information on the history of the Tatistcheff and other families relating to the Russian nobility. The Alexis.B. Tatistcheff papers also document his long career as an economist and language expert who served as an interpreter for the State Department.
Arrangement Statement
The collection arranged by the creator himself, and pasted to album sheets. Scrapbooks and albums have been unbound for preservation purposes. The collection is organized into six series: Tatistcheff family file, Obolenskii family file, Correspondence, Career file, Writings, and Printed matter.
Obolenskii family.; Romanov, House of.; Tatishchev family.; Russia--Court and courtiers.; Russia--History--Nicholas II, 1894-1917.; Russia--Nobility.; Russia.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations--United States.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations.
- Tatistcheff (Tatishchev) family file, 1878-1925
  Scope and Contents note
  Memoirs, notes, photo albums, and scrapbooks arranged by physical form.
  - Memorias, 1919-1977
    - "Crossing the Field," autobiography of Alexis B. Tatistcheff (Tatishchev),1903-1963, typed manuscript, twelve volumes (Box-folder 1:1-8/2:1-9/3:1-3)
    - "The Founder of the Tatistcheff (Tatishchev) Family, Vassily Yurevich (Vaslii Iur'evich), Prince Solomerskiy (Solomerskii), niknamed Tat-Istch," genealogy notes, typed manuscript on English, undated (Box-folder 3:4)
    - "The Tatistcheffs (Tatishchevs). History of a Family from 862 to 1949," by A. B. Tatistcheff (Tatishchev),typed manuscript in English, five volumes, 1976 (Box-folder 3:5-8)
      Includes family photographs
    - "Na rubezhe dvukh mirov," memorirs of Boris Alexeyevich Tatistcheff (Boris Alekseevich Tatishchev), (father), 1876-1946, typed manuscript in Russian, one volume (Box-folder 4:1-3)
    - "Reminiscences of Ekaterina Borisovna Tatistcheff (Ekaterina Borisovna Tatishchev), born Princess Mestcherskaia, my grandmother, 1848-1933, " typed manuscript in Russian, one volume (Box-folder 4:4)
    - "Zapiski Kniagini Marii Sergeevny Trubetskoi, ur. Lopukhinoi (Lopukhinoi)," (mother-In-law), typed manuscript in Russian, 1919 (Box-folder 4:5)
    - "Brief Histories of Some Russian Families Closely Related to the Tatistcheff (Tatishchev) Family," by A. B. Tatistcheff (Tatishchev). Typed manuscript in English, 1977 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Photographs, 1870-1925
    - Tatistcheffs (Tatishchev) family album, 1878-1925 (Box 8)
    - Tatishcheva (nee Bibikova), Varvara Mikhaïlovna (mother) photo album, 1885-1899 (Box 8)
    - "The last Tsar of Russia, Nicholas II, his court, military parades and exercises, Imperial hunting expeditions, etc.," photographs by Michael Alexis Tatistcheff (Mikhail Alekseevich Tatishchev), 1870-1913 (Box-folder 4:7-9)
  - Memorabilia, undated
    - Matrices for use in impressing the seal of Tatistcheff (Tatishchev) family on the metal buttons of the domestic male servants, two objects (Box 11)
    - Seal of the Tatitscheff (Tatishchev) family, one object (Box 11)
  - Scrapbooks, 1896-1966
    - "Documents pertaining to my father, Boris Alexeyevich Tatistcheff (Boris Alekseevich Tatishchev),", 1896-1966 (Box-folder 5:1-31)
    - "Album of Illustrations Pertaining to My Father's Voyage to France with the Tsar Nicholas II." Also contains some of my own and his pre-revolutionary Russian diplomatic passports and my family memorabilia,", 1901 (Othertype On shelf)
- Obolensky (Obolenskii) Family file, 1853-1971
  - "The Family of Princes Obolensky" (Obolenskii)," by Alexis B. Tatistcheff (Tatishchev), 1971 (Box-folder 5:32)
  - "Diaries of Prince Dimitriy Alexandrovich Obolensky (Dmitrii Aleksandrovich Obolenskii), my great grandfather, 1853-1879," typed manuscript in Russian, four volumes (Box 9-10)
- Correspondence, 1947-1977
  - General, 1967-1976 (Box-folder 5:33-34)
  - Allilueva, Svetlana, 1968-1973 (Box-folder 5:35)
  - Corbusier, Ernest, 1965 (Box-folder 5:36)
  - Grabbe, Georgii, 1970 (Box-folder 5:37)
  - Kennan, George, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 5:38)
  - Kisilev, Aleksandr, 1971 (Box-folder 5:39)
  - Korovaev, Petr Trofimovich, 1972 (Box-folder 5:40)
  - Novoe Russkoe Slovo, 1955-1977 (Box-folder 5:41)
    Includes clippings
  - Rakovskii, Mikhail Evgen'evich, 1977 (Box-folder 5:42)
  - Tatistcheff (Tatishchev), Boris A., 1976 (Box-folder 5:43)
  - Tiesenpausen, Andrei Dmitrievich, de, 1964-1976 (Box-folder 5:44-45)
  - Titorenko, Irina, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 5:46-47)
  - Prince Vasili Alexandrovich of Russia, 1976 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Archbishop Vitalii, 1947-1977 (Box-folder 6:2)
    Includes other materials on Russian Orthodox Church abroad.
- Career file, 1941-1976
  - A. B. Tatistcheff's (Tatishchev's) appointment as a Chief Statistician of the Commodity Exchange, Inc., 1941 (Box-folder 6:3)
  - "Documents Pertaining to FBI and CIA Investigations in Connection with My Security Clearances for Service in the US Federal Government and the United Nations, Annotated by Me," by A. B. Tatitscheff (A. B. Tatishchev), two volumes, 1941-1961 (Box-folder 6:4-7)
  - Correspondence, 1964 -1976
    Includes reports and memoranda.
    - General, 1964-1974 (Box-folder 6:8-10)
    - Cozanet, Claude, 1967 (Box-folder 6:11)
    - Fullbright, William J., 1968 (Box-folder 6:12)
    - Goldwater, Barry, 1976 (Box-folder 6:13)
    - Leon, Theodor H., 1965-1970 (Box-folder 6:14)
    - Lunney, Glynn S., 1972-1975 (Box-folder 6:15)
    - Stefan, Charles G., 1971 (Box-folder 6:16)
  - Miscellaneous documents pertaining to the United Nations activities in the former Belgian Congo, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 6:17)
    Includes correspondence, reports, and clippings.
  - Reports by A. B. Tatitscheff (Tatishchev) to the US Department of State on various assignments as escort interpreter, 1964-1975 (Box-folder 6:18-21/7:1-4)
- Writings, 1962-1975
  Arrangement note
  Arranged chronologically
  - "The Origins of the Rurikovichi: A Historical Essay," typescript in English, undated (Box-folder 7:5)
    Includes genealogical tables.
  - "Secret Agent," typed manuscript in English, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - "Tatizdat," unpublished articles, letters, etc. on various subjects, taped manuscripts in English and in Russian with some illustrations, three volumes, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 7:7-10)
  - "An Interesting Assignment," with illustrations, typed manuscript in English, 1972 (Box-folder 7:11)
- Printed matter, 1768-1915
  Separated Materials
  The issues of the following publications from boxes 2-3 and 11-12 have been separated from the collection to the Hoover Institution Library collection. Records for the material can be found through the Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/
  - Svod' Zakonov Rossiiskoi Imperii (Laws of the Russian Empire), edition, in Russian, two volumes, 1900
  - Bozherianov, Ivan Nikolaevich, Zhizneopisanie Imperatritsy Aleksadry Feodorovny suprugi Imperatora Nikolaia I, St. Peterburg, 1898
  - Dubenskii, D. M., Ego Imperatorskoe Velichestvo Gosudar' Imperator" Nikolai Aleksandrovich" v" diestvuiushchei armii, Sentiabr'-Oktiabr' 1914 g., Petrograd", 1915
  - Glinskoi, B. B., Tsarskiia dieti i ikh" nastavniki, Tsars', St. Petersburg, 1913
  - Shashkovskii, A. P., Ves' Peterburg" na 1913 god". Adresnaia i cpravochnaia kniga G. S.- Peterburga
  - Silvestre, Armand, La Russie, Paris, 1892
  - Tatistcheff, Serguey Spiridonovich (Tatishchev, Sergei Spiridonovich), Rod' Tatishchevykh". 1400-1900., published in on the 500th anniversary of the present name of the family
  - Tatistcheff (Tatishchev), Vasilii Nikitich, Istoriia Rossiiskaia s" samykh" drevneishikh" vremen" cherez" tridtsatl" let"(History of Russia from Ancient Times),four volumes, 1768-1784